Now that we know the correlation between pricing frameworks and project scope,
والآن وقد عرفنا العلاقة بين أطر التسعير ونطاق المشاريع
we're in a good position to see the pros and
فنحن في موضع جيد لرؤية إيجابيات
cons of the two pricing frameworks we discussed.
وسلبيات أطر التسعير التي ناقشناها.
First, let's take a look at the positives and
لنلق أولًا نظرة على النقاط الإيجابية
the negatives of using fixed cost as a pricing structure.
والسلبية لاستخدام التكلفة الثابتة كهيكل تسعيري.
First, is that the client can really lock in their budget for the project.
الأولى هي أن العميل يمكنه حقًا إحكام ميزانيته للمشروع.
They don't need to worry about things going over budget
فلا داعي للقلق بشأن تجاوز الميزانية
as long as the scope of the project remains the same.
طالما أن نطاق المشروع لم يتغير.
It also helps the freelancer to lock in
كما أنها تساعد الموظف الحر أيضًا في إحكام
a guaranteed amount that they can make from the project.
مبلغ مضمون يمكن تحقيقه من المشروع.
Next, indirect benefit from using a fixed cost approach is that there is
النقطة التالية هي أن الفائدة غير المباشرة من استخدام طريقة التكلفة الثابتة هي وجود
a thorough documentation of what we are going to work on before we start to work.
توثيق مفصل لما سوف نعمل عليه قبل البدء في العمل.
This often helps both the client and the freelancer to
وغالبًا ما يساعد هذا الأمر كلا من العميل والموظف الحر في
think through what really needs to get done in granular details,
التفكير في ما يجب فعلاً القيام به بأدق التفاصيل،
and also helps question our original assumptions about the end goal.
كما يساعدنا أيضًا في مراجعة افتراضاتنا الأولية بشأن الهدف النهائي.
On the other hand,
وعلى الجانب الآخر،
the flexibility to change things is very limited in a fixed cost project.
تكون المرونة اللازمة لتغيير الأمور محدودة جدًا في مشاريع التكلفة الثابتة.
For example, if the client wants to involve the scope
فإذا أراد العميل مثلًا استخدام نطاق
of one particular module or add a new module,
نموذج بعينها أو إضافة نموذج جديدة
the fixed cost needs to be recalculated by the freelancer based on
فسوف يكون على الموظف الحر أن يعيد حساب التكلفة الثابتة بناء على
the extra effort needed and get a sign-off from the client to change it for the project.
المجهود الإضافي المطلوب، وأن يحصل على موافقة العميل على إجراء هذا التغيير للمشروع.
If this happens multiple times during the course of the project,
إذا حدث هذا الأمر عدة مرات خلال المشروع
it can become quite tedious for the project,
يمكن أن يصبح المشروع مملاً للغاية،
especially if there are contracts involved.
خاصة إذا كانت هناك عقود.
Let me give an example from my own experience.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالًا من خبرتي الشخصية.
I had sent a shot expression of interests to
لقد أرسلت رسالة التعبير عن الاهتمام بالعمل
a client who belonged to a big multinational company.
لعميل كان يعمل لدى شركة كبيرة متعددة الجنسيات.
The client had sent a specification of what they wanted to get
وكان العميل قد أرسل المواصفات لما كان يريد أن
built with a suggested price of $2,500.
يتم بناؤه بمبلغ مقترح كان قيمته 2,500 دولار أمريكي.
When I looked at the specification which was at a high level,
عندما نظرت في المواصفات التي كانت عالية المستوى
I suggested to them that based on the effort involved,
اقترحت على العميل أنه بناء على المجهود المطلوب
it seems to be at least $6,000 but we'll need to make
فيبدو أن الأمر سيتطلب 6,000 دولار أمريكي على الأقل، ولكننا نحتاج أيضًا لجعل
the requirements much more specific to quote an exact estimate.
متطلبات العمل أكثر تحديدًا حتى يمكننا وضع تقدير دقيق.
Also while I was talking to them,
وبينما كنت أتحدث إليه
I did not lose the opportunity to talk about their aspects of the project.
لم أفوت فرصة التطرق إلى جوانب المشروع الخاصة به.
I suggested solutions, different ways in which we can build their solution,
فاقترحت حلولًا وطرقًا مختلفة لتنفيذ الحلول الخاصة به
different optimizations that we can do to the recurrent infrastructure.
وتحسينات مختلفة يمكننا إجراءها على البنية التحتية الحالية.
To cut the long story short,
باختصار،
the requirements could not be specified in detail eventually,
لم نتمكن في آخر الأمر من تحديد المتطلبات بالتفصيل
and I did get the project at an hourly rate.
وعملت على المشروع بالأجر في الساعة.
Now, as we walked along,
والآن، ونحن نتابع،
their requirements kept on changing,
كانت متطلباته تتغير باستمرار
new modules were added.
تم إضافة وحدات جديدة.
Some things were changed,
وتغيرت بعض الأشياء
but then we changed back to
ولكنها أُعيدت إلى
their original form based on how their management wanted it to be.
صورتها الأولى بناء على ما أراده رؤساء عمل العميل.
Based on the time spent,
بناء على الوقت الذي قضيته على المشروع
I ended up charging around $17,500 to
انتهى بي الأمر بأن طالبت العميل بـ 17,500 دولار أمريكي
the client which they had originally estimated at $2,500,
العميل الذي قدّره في الأصل بمبلغ 2500 دولار أمريكي،
with a not so detailed requirements spec.
بمواصفات مطلوبة غير محددة جيدًا.
I also got more projects from the same client
حصلت أيضًا على مشاريع أخرى من نفس العميل
totaling my revenue to $50,000 from the same client.
ليبلغ مجموع العائد الذي حصلت عليه من نفس العميل 50,000 دولار أمريكي.
Now, let's look at the positives and the negatives of
والآن لننظر في النقاط السلبية والإيجابية
using time and material as the pricing structure.
لاستخدام الوقت والمادة كأساس هيكل التسعير.
First, the biggest advantage is
أولًا، الميزة الأهم هي
that the scope can evolve during the course of the project.
أن إطار العمل قد يتطور أثناء العمل على المشروع.
If the client changes their mind after looking at the first module,
إذا غير العميل رأيه بعد الإطلاع على النموذج الأول،
they're free to change the design of the second module,
فله حرية تغيير التصميم في النموذج الثاني،
or even completely remove the second module and go right to the third one, and so on.
أو حتى إلغاء النموذج الثاني بالكامل والقفز إلى النموذج الثالث وهكذا.
There's no locking order front commitment here in the time and materials contract.
فليس هناك إلزام مستقبلي مسبق للفترة الزمنية لعقد الوقت والمواد.
If the client is not happy with the freelancers work,
فإن كان العميل غير سعيد بالخدمة التي يقدمها له الموظف الحر،
or you as a freelancer is not happy with the client's work culture or the paperwork,
أو إن كنت أنت كموظف حر غير سعيد بأسلوب العميل أو نظام عمله،
either party is free to leave the project after
فكلا الطرفين له حرية إنهاء العمل بعد
settling the payment based on the time taken to do the work so far.
تسوية المستحقات المالية طبقًا للوقت الذي استغرقه العمل حتى اللحظة.
Honestly, unless you really have to,
وفي الحقيقة إن لم تكن بالفعل مضطرًا لترك المشروع،
it's not a good idea to leave any client's project in
فلا أنصحك أبدًا بالانسحاب من أي مشروع لأي عميل
between even if you do not have a contractual obligation.
في منتصف الطريق، حتى وإن لم تكن مُلزمًا بالاستمرار طبقًا للعقد.
Remember, if you focus on maximizing the value for the client,
وتذكر! إن ركزت على تعظيم القيمة للعميل،
it will pay you in the long run.
فستجد المقابل على المدى البعيد.
Now, since the scope is not fixed,
والآن بما أن السياق غير ثابت،
the client does not have to sign
فالعميل ليس مضطرًا لتوقيع
new contracts every time they make a change in the project,
عقود جديدة في كل مرة يُعدل على المشروع
or if they have you started on entirely new project.
أو يجعلك تبدأ العمل على مشروع جديد بالكامل.
Since it is a time and material contract,
وبما أنه عقد زمني ومادي،
or an early model contract and it's often called,
أو عقد نموذجي أولي كما يُطلق عليه غالبًا،
the obligation is to pay based on the time irrespective of the work done.
فإن الإلزام يكمن في تسديد المستحقات المالية على أساس الوقت، بغض النظر عن العمل المُنجز.
But take that with a pinch of salt.
ولكن هناك بعض التحفظ على هذا الكلام.
If the client hires you to build a web app,
فليس من المعقول أن يُوظفك العميل لعمل تطبيق إلكتروني،
they cannot have you make a rocket to go to the moon at the same rate.
ثم يطلب منك عمل الأعاجيب على التطبيق وبنفس المقابل المادي.
Even in the time and material pricing frameworks,
ففي إطار الوقت والتسعير،
a very high level scope of work is generally agreed upon.
هناك سياق وإطار عام للعمل يجب الاتفاق عليه.
Again, the downside of time and materials
ومرة أخرى يتمثل الجانب السلبي لإطار عمل الوقت والمهام
framework is that there is no upper limit on the budget.
في عدم وجود حد أعلى للميزانية.
Client's budget can keep going higher and higher as the project moves.
ويمكن لميزانية العميل أن تستمر في الارتفاع كلما زاد العمل على المشروع.
With some clients may not be quite comfortable with,
وقد لا يكون ذلك مريحًا لبعض العملاء،
but as we discussed earlier,
ولكننا ناقشنا سابقًا،
some projects may have a cap on the number of hours that you can spend on the project.
قد يكون لبعض المشاريع حد أقصى لعدد الساعات التي يمكن أن تقضيها في المشروع.
But that's said, the work that can be done in these hours is not fixed.
ولكن في الواقع، فالعمل الذي قد تقوم به خلال هذه الساعات غير ثابت.
If the client wants to get more work done and the cap is done with,
إذا أراد العميل أن يُنجز المزيد من العمل مع انتهاء الحد الأقصى لساعات المشروع،
they mainly do increase their budget.
فهنا يقوم بزيادة ميزانية المشروع.
An interesting downside of the time and
وهناك جانب سلبي مهم بالنسبة لنظام تسعير الوقت
material pricing structure is that if you are highly skilled in your area of expertise,
والمهام، فلو كنت ماهر جدًا في مجال خبرتك،
it may not be very efficient for you.
فقد لا يفيدك كثيرًا هذا النظام.
For example, you might be able to do something in 15 minutes,
فعلى سبيل المثال، قد يمكنك إتمام مهمة ما في 15 دقيقة،
which an averagely skilled freelancer may take more than an hour to complete.
بينما قد تستغرق نفس المهمة أكثر من ساعة حين يعمل عليها موظف حر متوسط الكفاءة.
Fifteen minutes of your time may not earn
خمسة عشر دقيقة من وقتك قد لا تكسب فيها
enough revenue for you but it could be a lot of value for the client.
العائد المناسب لك، ولكن القيمة مقابل السعر تكون عظيمة للعميل.
But since you are paid based on the time spend,
ولكن بما أنك تتلقى أجرك مقابل الوقت،
you only get paid for those 15 minutes.
فستحصل فقط على أجر الـ 15 دقيقة.